<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      version="5.0">
    <title>OpenStack Extension Registry Proposal</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Jorge</firstname>
                <surname>Williams</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Rackspace Cloud</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <copyright>
            <year>2011</year>
            <holder>Rackspace US, Inc.</holder>
        </copyright>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
            The extension registry should be modeled after the OpenGL
            extensions registry:<link
            xlink:href="http://www.opengl.org/registry/">
            http://www.opengl.org/registry/ </link>.  The OpenStack
            extension registry serves the following purposes:
        </para>
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It provides a central repository for all OpenStack
                    extensions organized by <abbrev>API</abbrev>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It allows vendors to register vendor prefixes: (RAX,
                    HP, etc.).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            Note that this proposal is for a repository of extension
            specifications and <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis>
            a repository of extension software or plugins for a
            particular OpenStack implementation.  That is, the
            repository is implementation agnostic and may describe
            extensions supported by implementations other than the
            OpenStack reference implementations (Nova, Glance, Swift,
            Keystone).
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Benefits of a centralized repository</title>
        <para>
            Users of OpenStack APIs benefit from having a centralized
            extension repository.  While we would like to encourage
            vendors to develop extensions in coordination with the
            OpenStack community, some vendors may opt to develop their
            extensions independently. Without a centralized extension
            repository, users would have to gather information from
            various vendor websites in order to burst from one cloud
            onto another.  Adding to the confusion is the fact that
            vendor
            <inlineequation><mathphrase>X</mathphrase></inlineequation>
            may choose to provide support for an extension developed
            by vendor
            <inlineequation><mathphrase>Y</mathphrase></inlineequation>.
            It may, therefore, not be clear to users where to go to
            get information about an extension.
        </para>
        <para>
            Extension authors also benefit from having a central
            repository. The repository can be used to determine
            whether an existing extension satisfies an author's
            requirements. This can help mitigate the problem of
            extension proliferation and it may provide an opportunity
            for authors of similar extensions to combine their
            efforts.  Additionally, the repository may provide a means
            by which users can become aware of extensions not
            currently supported by their vendors, thus allowing them
            to lobby for such support.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Extension Registration</title>
        <para>
            The extension registration process closely follows the
            registration process developed by the Khronos group for
            OpenGL:
            <link
            xlink:href="http://www.opengl.org/registry/doc/rules.html">
            http://www.opengl.org/registry/doc/rules.html</link>.
            When creating an extension the following steps should be
            followed:
        </para>
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Determine if an existing extension can be used</title>
                    <para>
                        Reuse of an existing extension is encouraged
                        as this helps prevent the unnecessary
                        proliferation of extensions and provides a
                        means by which popular extension can be
                        promoted to the core.  Additionally, it's
                        possible that existing extensions have
                        established client support.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
                <para>
                    If an extension with similar functionality exists,
                    but does not entirely meet the authors needs, then
                    authors are encouraged to collaborate on promoting
                    the extension into a multi-vendor extension.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Finally, an extension may be under development but
                    has not yet been released. Thus, authors are also
                    encouraged to send an email to the OpenStack
                    mailing list to see if anyone else is working on
                    an extension with similar functionality.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Determine if a multi-vendor extension is
                    appropriate</title>
                    <para>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Register a vendor prefix, if one has not
                    already been assigned</title>
                    <para>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Develop and write the extension specification</title>
                    <para>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Freeze the specification and submit it to
                    the registry</title>
                    <para>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Make the registry the source of truth for
                    the specification</title>
                    <para>
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
</article>
