<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      version="5.0">
    <title>OpenStack Extension Registry Proposal</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Jorge</firstname>
                <surname>Williams</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Rackspace Cloud</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <copyright>
            <year>2011</year>
            <holder>Rackspace US, Inc.</holder>
        </copyright>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>
            The extension registry should be modeled after the OpenGL
            extensions registry:<link
            xlink:href="http://www.opengl.org/registry/">
            http://www.opengl.org/registry/ </link>.  The OpenStack
            extension registry serves the following purposes:
        </para>
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It provides a central repository for all OpenStack
                    extensions organized by <abbrev>API</abbrev>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It allows vendors to register vendor prefixes: (RAX,
                    HP, etc.).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
            Note that this proposal is for a repository of extension
            specifications and <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis>
            a respository of extension software or plugins for a
            particular OpenStack implementaton.  That is, the
            repository is implementation augnostic and may describe
            extensions supported by implementations other than the
            OpenStack reference implmentation (Nova, Glance, Swift,
            Keystone).
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Benefites of a centralized repository</title>
        <para>
            Users of OpenStack APIs benefit from having a centralized
            extension repository.  While we would like to encourage
            vendors to develop extensions in coordination with the
            OpenStack community, some vendors may opt to develop their
            extensions independently. Without a centralized extension
            repository, users would have to gather information from
            various vendor websites in order to burst from one cloud
            onto another.  Adding to the confusion is the fact that
            vendor
            <inlineequation><mathphrase>X</mathphrase></inlineequation>
            may choose to provide support for an extension developed
            by vendor
            <inlineequation><mathphrase>Y</mathphrase></inlineequation>.
            It may, therefore, not be clear to users where to go to
            get information about an extension.
        </para>
        <para>
            Extension authors also benefit from having a central
            repository. The repository can be used to determine
            whether an existing extension satisfies an author's
            requirements. This can help mitigate the problem of
            extension proliferation and it may provide an opertunity
            for authors of similar extensions to combine their
            efforts.  Additionally, the repository may provide a means
            by which users can become aware of extensions not
            currently supported by their vendors, allowing them to
            lobby for such support.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Vendor Prefixes</title>
        <para>
            
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Extension Registration</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </section>
</article>
